today we'll take a look at one of the
largest insurance companies in Canada
and we'll make a full stock analysis on
the company manual life with the deer
MFC as always after checking their
business model so all are able to
generate their income I'll make a quick
fundamental analysis followed by price
prediction to determine what is the true
intrinsic value of this company without
further Ado let's get do it right now
manual life is currently the largest
Canadian insurance companies in terms of
its assets under management and it is
also ranking in the top 10 worldwide in
this sector with many hundred of billion
of dollars under its management add to
this with a Workforce that exceeds
40,000 employees with many agents and
partners this company that is currently
Worth close to $60 billion as over 30
million customers all around the globe
as any great financial institution
manual life is offering a wide range of
products and services to their customers
such as great life insurance health
insurance and travel insurance but also
credit cards loans bank accounts and
investing products an excellent news
about Manu life is that they are able to
offer these products and services
worldwide to many different places in
Canada in the US in Europe and in Asia
in 2023 these products and services have
helped manual life to generate over $6.3
billion of core earnings which actually
represents an increase of about 15%
compared to 2022 this important growth
has been driven by two important factors
where we know that their insurance
product sales have been increasing
year-over-year of about 22% and where on
the side their investing products have
been increasing by about 15% year
over-year but still at the moment you
might be wondering hey but Louis how
does an insurance company is able to
generate the biggest part of their total
income well in fact you need to know
that most insurance companies generate
the biggest part of their income from
two main sources first they are charging
premiums to their different clients in
exchange of insurance coverage and then
they are reinvesting those premiums into
interest generating assets as we will
see later on in their impressive
portfolio at the end of the day for the
investors it means that it is super
important to understand how many new
policies have been sold throughout the
last year to be able to know what is the
total sum of all of the premiums of the
company but you also want to be sure
that the company isn't using too much of
their premiums to pay the different
incidents that have occurred to their
clients it is why in the case of this
analysis we'll take a look at the annual
premium equivalent aka the AP but we
also glance at the contractual service
margin aka the CSM first DP represent
the total annualized value of all the
new single premiums combined with the
recurring premium policies so it
represents the sum of the total value of
regular or recurring Premium Plus 10% of
any new single premiums written for the
fiscal year in the case of Manu life the
great news is that for the fourth
quarter of 2023 their AP sales have been
increasing by 20% up to $1.6 billion for
the quarter now for the CSM this
represents the unearned profit that the
company expect to earn as it provides
different services for man life the
other great news is that for the Q4 of
2023 we've seen that this number has
been increasing up by 41% to
$626 million these are all some pretty
encouraging news for the investors that
are showing that this company is able to
continuously grow their total sales of
their new policies but what is also
pretty interesting is the fact that the
company is also able to generate quite a
lot of money from its different
investing portfolio as I told you
earlier the first source of income from
manual life is made by selling different
new premiums but then all of these new
and recuring premiums are we invest in
our massive $417 billion asset portfolio
in this incredible portfolio we find
that about 50% of their total assets are
invest in different corporate and
government bonds and then the rest is
invest in other asset classes such as
public Equity private debt mortgage real
estate and Farm land plus the excellent
news is that more than 96% of the total
bonds that are added in this portfolio
are considered as some investment Gres
investment this means that those bonds
have a rating of 3B or more meaning that
they are quite safe for the investors
all of these great news have made that
the company has been able to beat the
analy predictions in terms of their
earnings per share predicted at .85 per
share and reported at 92 per share plus
since one year we can see that the
company is up by more than 20% where
since the beginning of 2024 we can see
that it has been up by over 10% so now
let's see what the valuation metrics are
telling us about the true intrinsic
value of manual life the first thing we
can notice is that manual Life currently
worth about $ 58 billion but with a
pretty low price to earnings ratio of
only about 12 combined with excellent
price to sales and Price to Book ratio
of only about 1.40 those metrics are
showing that this company would
currently be quite undervalued at the
moment in terms of the profitability of
this insurance company we can see that
over the last 12 months they've been
able to achieve some incredible profit
and operating margin as well as a fair
return on Equity over the last 12 months
of about
11.57% add to this as I just told you
this company is able to generate quite a
lot of total revenue and a lot of
Revenue growth where we can see that
over the last 12 months they've been
able to generate over $27 billion of
Revenue new but what is truly
astonishing is their quar revenue growth
year-over-year of about
39% and their great quar earnings growth
year-over year of about close to 100%
plus as any great financial company this
company always keep quite a lot of cash
with about $26 billion in cash at the
moment compared to a smaller debt of
only about $22 billion which makes that
its debt to equity ratio is only about
45% now in terms of the volatility of
the company represents by the bet on a 5
years period we can see that the company
is slightly more volatile than the
overall Market with a beta of more than
one but over the last 52 weeks we can
see that this company hasn't been able
to achieve the same performance as for
the overall Market nevertheless what is
pretty interesting about manual life is
that they are giving close to 5% of
dividend with only a payout ratio of
less than 60% and so this is showing
that the company isn't using too much of
their earnings to pay the dividends to
their shareholders which means that the
company could eventually even grow more
their total dividend over the next
couple of years now in terms of their
total revenue we can see that despite
important decrease in them in 2022 we
can see that over the last year they've
been able to come back to some pretty
normal level with some important growth
and so it has been translated that
despite some pretty negative net income
in 2022 in 2023 they've come back with
some incredible growth with some net
income of close to $5.5 billion but now
to determine what is the true entrancing
value of manual life as always we'll be
using many different valuation models
starting with the pillar Lynch valuation
one which is a simple formula where you
add the future growth of the earnings
per share with the dividend yield and
that you divide with the price to
earnings ratio and with all of these
inputs we find that the stock would
currently be quite fairly valued close
to being undervalued right now
unfortunately for your dividend
discounted model we won't be able to use
it because our average growth rate is
currently higher than our weight average
cost of capital Plus in terms of the
discounted cash flow model as always
we'll be trying first to find what is
our weight average cost of capital and
to do so we need to find what is the
cost of debt the cost of equity and the
cost of debt in equity to find what is
our weight average cost of capital of
close to 10% and so by simply
discounting what are our future free
cash flow that are predicted we are able
to find what is the true intrinsic value
of this business that is close to 173
at the moment and so according to these
metrics we find that the company would
currently be quite massively undervalued
right now and finally we'll be using the
Gram's original value formula and the
GRS revised value formula and so with
both of these models we can find that
our company would also be quite
massively undervalued right now as
you've been able to see in this video
Manu life is definitely a top pick for
anyone looking for a company that is
able to grow their total premium sales
year after year with this simple
business model combined with an
excellent investing portfolio of more
than 400 billion dollar it is fair to
say that manual life is there to stay at
the same time with some pretty fair
valuation metrics and with some great
dividend growth over the past 5 years
with a dividend kill that is close to 5%
right now it is personally a company in
which I am invest and that I'm able to
reinvest all the dividends that I
receive every single quarter to buy new
shares of it but now on your side if
you're looking to find other great
stocks that are currently quite
undervalued right now on the stock
market well check out the video that's
going to be right over here and I will
see you soon peace